<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../../lib/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<section id="sec-tutorial" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Tutorials</title>

  <para>
	This section contains a series of Flashlight tutorials.

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis>PlanetBaron</emphasis> &ndash; Investigating a client-server real-time strategy game
			that has some concurrency problems we'll use Flashlight to uncover and fix. This tutorial
			is presented in <xref linkend="sec-tutorial-planetbaron-client" /> (a GUI thread-confinement bug),
			<xref linkend="sec-tutorial-planetbaron-server" /> (a race condition),
			and <xref linkend="sec-tutorial-planetbaron-playerui" /> (a potential deadlock).</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para><emphasis>Dining Philosophers</emphasis> &ndash;
			Using Flashlight to investigate a Java implementation of the classic dining
			philosophers problem that may deadlock. This tutorial is
			presented in <xref
			linkend="sec-tutorial-dining"/>.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>(Android Only) <emphasis>Counter Race</emphasis> &ndash; Fixing a troubled implementation of a concurrent
			counting Android application. This tutorial focuses on how to launch and collect data from Android applications using
			Flashlight. If you do not have the Android Developer Tools (ADT) installed in your Eclipse as well as the
			Android plug-ins for Flashlight then this tutorial cannot be loaded and run.
			This tutorial is presented in
			 <xref linkend="sec-tutorial-android" />.</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>(Advanced/Optional) <emphasis>Using the Flashlight query editor</emphasis> &ndash; This is an advanced tutorial that
			shows how to change queries in the Flashlight tool.
			This tutorial is presented in
			 <xref linkend="sec-tutorial-query-editor" />.</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      
      
  It is recommended that you go through these tutorials in order.  It is also
  recommended that these tutorials be performed "hands-on" at your
  computer. You might want to create a new Eclipse workspace to use for
  these tutorials. In addition, if you run into any difficulties as you
  step through the tutorials please consider sending us a tip for
  improvement as described in <xref linkend="sec-bugs-and-tips"/>.</para>

 <figure id="fig-tutorial-installing-projects">
    <title>Menu item to install tutorial projects into your workspace</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/tutorial-installing-projects.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>These tutorials assume that you have installed Flashlight. If you see a
  <guimenu>Flashlight</guimenu> menu item on your Eclipse main menu than you can
  assume it has been installed properly.  To follow along with the tutorials you
  will also need to add the tutorial projects to your workspace.  From the
  Eclipse main menu, choose
  <menuchoice><guimenu>Flashlight</guimenu><guimenuitem>Run Flashlight
  Tutorials</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and add
  all the listed projects) to your workspace as
  displayed in <xref linkend="fig-tutorial-installing-projects" /> and <xref
  linkend="fig-tutorial-installing-projects-dialog" />. All the projects should
  be checked when you open the dialog.</para>

  <figure id="fig-tutorial-installing-projects-dialog">
    <title>Adding the tutorial projects to your workspace</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/tutorial-installing-projects-dialog.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
      <note>
		<title>FlashlightTutorial_CounterRace is an Android application</title>

		<para>The <guilabel>FlashlightTutorial_CounterRace</guilabel> project requires
		that both the Android Developer Tools (ADT) and the
			Android plug-ins for Flashlight be installed in your Eclipse. If they are
			not this project will not appear in <xref linkend="fig-tutorial-installing-projects-dialog" />.
			If you do not use Android missing this project is no problem. Simply skip that portion of
			the tutorial.</para>
	</note>
	
	      <note>
		<title>FlashlightTutorial_DiningPhilosophersJava8 is a Java 8 only application</title>

		<para>The <guilabel>FlashlightTutorial_DiningPhilosophersJava8</guilabel> project requires
		Java 8. If your Eclipse and your JDK support Java 8 you can load this project and use
		it for the tutorial presented in <xref linkend="sec-tutorial-dining"/>. If you do not
		yet develop Java 8 code then the <guilabel>FlashlightTutorial_DiningPhilosophers</guilabel> project is the
		one to select. You do not need both projects, simply uncheck the one you don't need,
		but can load both if you are using Java 8.</para>
	</note>

  <xi:include href="tutorial-planetbaron-client.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="tutorial-planetbaron-server.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="tutorial-planetbaron-playerui.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="tutorial-dining-philosophers.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="tutorial-android.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="tutorial-query-editor.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="tutorial-maven.xml"/>
</section>
