<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../../lib/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<section id="sec-tutorial" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Tutorials</title>

  <para>This section contains a series of Flashlight tutorials.  It is
  recommended that you go through these tutorials in order.  It is also
  recommended that these tutorials be performed "hands-on" at your
  computer. You might want to create a new Eclipse workspace to use for
  these tutorials. In addition, if you run into any difficulties as you
  step through the tutorials please consider sending us a tip for
  improvement as described in <xref linkend="sec-bugs-and-tips"/>.</para>

 <figure id="fig-tutorial-installing-projects">
    <title>Menu item to install tutorial projects into your workspace</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/tutorial-installing-projects.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>These tutorials assume that you have installed Flashlight. If you see a
  <guimenu>Flashlight</guimenu> menu item on your Eclipse main menu than you can
  assume it has been installed properly.  To follow along with the tutorials you
  will also need to add the PlanetBaron project to your workspace.  From the
  Eclipse main menu, choose
  <menuchoice><guimenu>Flashlight</guimenu><guimenuitem>Run Flashlight
  Tutorials</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and add
  <application>FlashlightTutorial_PlanetBaron</application> to your workspace as
  displayed in <xref linkend="fig-tutorial-installing-projects" /> and <xref
  linkend="fig-tutorial-planetbaron-install" />.</para>

  <figure id="fig-tutorial-planetbaron-install">
    <title>Adding PlanetBaron to your workspace</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/tutorial-planetbaron-install.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
      <note>
		<title>New Flashlight Launched Run Control Dialog</title>

		<para>The <guilabel>Flashlight Launched Run Control</guilabel> dialog
		now lists each launched instrumented application. It lets you track the progress
		of the application from launch, through, collection, data preparation, to being ready
		to query in the Flashlight perspective. This dialog lets you stop data collection on
		a running process at any time. The use of this dialog is not fully described below but
		is straightforward to use. For example, prompts to prepare data no longer occur. When
		the run completes it is prepared. The dialog is discussed in the Android tutorial because
		it is critical to avoid having to <emphasis>Force Stop</emphasis> applications on the
		phone or tablet.</para>
	</note>

  <xi:include href="sect2-sec-tutorial-client.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="sect2-sec-tutorial-server.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="sect2-sec-tutorial-playerui.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="sect2-sec-tutorial-query-editor.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="sect2-sec-tutorial-android.xml"/>
</section>
