<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../lib/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<section id="sec-bugs-and-tips">
  <title>Bugs and tips</title>

  <para>Flashlight allows any user to send problem reports and
  suggestions to SureLogic from the main menu. Selecting
  <guimenuitem>Send Tip for Improvement</guimenuitem> or
  <guimenuitem>Send Problem Report</guimenuitem> allows a tip or problem
  report to be send to SureLogic directly within Eclipse as shown in
  <xref linkend="fig-bugs-and-tips-main-menu-service" />. These menu
  choices bring up dialogs that allow the user to control exactly what
  information is sent to SureLogic.  In addition, the user can preview
  the exact text that will be sent over the internet.</para>

  <figure id="fig-bugs-and-tips-main-menu-service">
    <title>Menu items to send bugs and tips to SureLogic</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/bugs-and-tips-main-menu-service.png"/></imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>The <guimenuitem>Send Tip for Improvement</guimenuitem> command
  opens a dialog to allow entry of a suggestion by the user to improve
  the Flashlight tool as seen in <xref
  linkend="fig-bugs-and-tips-menu-send-tip" />. The dialog allows the
  user to control exactly what information is sent to SureLogic. In addition, the
  user can preview and edit the exact text that will be sent. If you have no
  Internet connection you can print or save the text of your problem report (to fax or email).</para>

  <figure id="fig-bugs-and-tips-menu-send-tip">
    <title>Dialog allowing the user to enter a tip to improve Flashlight</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/bugs-and-tips-menu-send-tip.png"/></imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>The <guimenuitem>Send Problem Report</guimenuitem> command opens
  a dialog to allow entry of a problem report by the user about the
  Flashlight tool as seen in <xref
  linkend="fig-bugs-and-tips-menu-problem-report" />. The dialog allows
  the user to control exactly what information is sent to SureLogic. In addition,
  the user can preview and edit the exact text that will be sent. If you have no
  Internet connection you can print or save the text of your problem report (to fax or email).</para>

  <figure id="fig-bugs-and-tips-menu-problem-report">
    <title>Dialog allowing the user to enter a problem report about Flashlight</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/bugs-and-tips-menu-problem-report.png"/></imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>Messages sent from these dialogs go over HTTP to SureLogic. If a
  proxy is used on your network then it is critical to configure Eclipse
  to use it.  To do this open the Eclipse
  <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> and examine the <guilabel>Network
  Connections</guilabel> under the <guilabel>General</guilabel>
  preferences.  This dialog allows you to configure Eclipse for your
  network as shown in <xref
  linkend="fig-bugs-and-tips-network-connections" />.</para>

  <figure id="fig-bugs-and-tips-network-connections">
    <title>Eclipse preferences for network connections within the IDE</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/bugs-and-tips-network-connections.png"/></imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
</section>
