<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../lib/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<sect1 id="flashlight-perspective">
  <title>The Flashlight perspective</title>

  <para>The <guilabel>Flashlight</guilabel> perspective organizes the Eclipse
  workbench to show views which will help you to interact with data from program
  runs.</para>

  <para>This perspective is useful for beginning use of the Flashlight tool. Its
  "canned" organization can help you to understand the capabilities of the tool.
  Advanced users may want to reconfigure the screen layout and save a custom
  perspective.</para>

  <informalfigure id="fig-flashlight-perspective">
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/flashlight-perspective.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>

  <sect2>
    <title>Views</title>
    <para>This section describes the various Flashlight views unique to the
    Flashlight Eclipse client, and that populate the perspective</para>

    <sect3 id="flashlight-runs-view">
      <title>Flashlight Runs</title>
      <para>
	The <guilabel>Flashlight Runs</guilabel> view lists information about
	all of the completed runs of programs launched from the Flashlight
	launch tab.

	<itemizedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title>Raw</title>
	      <para>The size of the data produced by the program run.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title>Prep</title>
	      <para>The size of the data produced by prepping the run.  If the
	      data has not been prepared yet, this column will be blank.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title>Run</title>
	      <para>The name of the program run.  This is the same name that you
	      see when launching a program from the Flashlight launch
	      tab.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title>Time</title>
	      <para>The time the program was launched.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title>By</title>
	      <para>The user the program ran under.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title>Host</title>
	      <para>The hostname of the computer the program ran on.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title>Java</title>
	      <para>The version of the JVM that ran the program.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title>Vendor</title>
	      <para>The JVM vendor.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title>OS</title>
	      <para>The operating system the program ran under.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title>Max Memory (MB)</title>
	      <para>The maximum amount of memory in megabytes allotted to the
	      program.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    <formalpara>
	      <title>Processors</title>
	      <para>The number of CPU's that the JVM ran on when this program
	      was executed.</para>
	    </formalpara>
	  </listitem>
	</itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <informalfigure id="fig-flashlight-runs-view">
	<!--title>The Flashlight Runs View</title-->
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/flashlight-runs-view.png" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>

    </sect3>

    <sect3 id="flashlight-run-overview">
      <title>Run Overview</title>
      <para>
        The <guilabel>Run Overview</guilabel> view displays a summary of the
        data Flashlight collected for a given run.  The overview for a run is
        displayed whenever a run is selected in the <guilabel>Run
        View</guilabel>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The collected data is organized into a series of tabs, each focusing on
        a facet of the data.
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Lock Contention</title>
              <para>Lists the most highly contended locks in the program, sorted
              in descended order by average block time.  Drilling into the lock
              will display all of the code locations where the lock was acquired
              during the run, and how long the program was blocked for.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Deadlocks</title>
              <para>Allows the user to browse all detected lock cycles in the
              program. Each cycle has a numeric identifier, and is displayed as
              a link at the top of the page. Clicking on the cycle's link will
              display a graph of the cycle.  The nodes in the graph represent
              lock objects in the program, and each directed edge indicates that
              the target node was acquired while the source node was held at
              some point in the run.  The edges are also displayed as hyperlinks
              to the right of the graph, and clicking on an edge shows example
              stack traces for both source and target node acquisitions.  The
              threads that contributed to this lock cycle are also shown, and
              hovering over them with the mouse highlights the edges observed in
              that thread.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Race Conditions</title>
              <para>Displays a tree of all the fields for which a potential race
              condition was detected during the run.  Clicking on a field will
              display a list of all of the locks that were held while the field
              was accessed, and when and where the locks were acquired.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Bad Publishes</title>
              <para>Displays a tree of all the fields that were written to and
              read by multiple threads before their owning object was fully
              constructed. Drilling into a field shows all of the events that
              occurred during object construction, and clicking on an event
              displays the event's full stack trace underneath the tree.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Program Timeline</title>
              <para>A timeline of the observed run. The timeline shows the
              duration of each thread as a blue line, and displays the full
              program duration in red.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Coverage</title>
              <para>Shows the entire call graph of the observed program as a
              tree, as well as the names of every thread.  Clicking on a thread
              will narrow the call graph down to just the portion of the program
              observed in that that thread.  Multiple threads can also be
              selected and deselected by shift-clicking.
              </para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <informalfigure id="fig-flashlight-run-overview">
	<!--title>The Flashlight Run Overview</title-->
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/flashlight-run-overview.png" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>

    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Query Menu</title>
      <para>
	The <guilabel>Query Menu</guilabel> view displays the queries that can
	be run from the current query results displayed in the <guilabel>Query
	Results</guilabel> view.  If no results are displayed, then it displays
	the queries that can be run from the currently selected run in the
	<guilabel>Flashlight Runs</guilabel> view.  Queries that can be run by
	double-clicking are black, queries that need you to select a more
	specific row from the <guilabel>Query Results</guilabel> view are grayed
	out.
      </para>
      <informalfigure id="fig-flashlight-query-menu-view">
	<!--title>The Query Menu View</title-->
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/flashlight-query-menu-view.png" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>

    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Query Results</title>
      <para>
	This view displays the results from performing a query on a Flashlight
	run.  You can change the results displayed by clicking on a different
	query in the <guilabel>Query Results Explorer</guilabel> view or in the
	<guilabel>Query Menu</guilabel> view.  Only one of the Query Results and
	Run Overview views are displayed at a time.
      </para>

      <para>
	The result of a query is displayed as either a tree, table, or
	tree-table, depending on the specific query.  <xref
	linkend="query-reference"/> describes the different queries and the
	shapes of their results.
      </para>
      
      <informalfigure id="fig-flashlight-query-results-view">
	<!--title>The Query Results View</title-->
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/flashlight-query-results-view.png" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>

    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Query Results Explorer</title>
	<para>
	  This view allows you to select any of the queries run previously
	  during the session and display it in the <guilabel>Query
	  Results</guilabel> view.  You can also delete any or all of the
	  results from here.
	</para>
      <informalfigure id="fig-flashlight-query-results-explorer-view">
	<!--title>The Query Results Explorer View</title-->
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/flashlight-query-results-explorer-view.png" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
    </sect3>

    <sect3>
      <title>Historical Source Snapshot</title>
      <para>
	When a Flashlight run is performed, a snapshot of the project source
	code is collected.  This view shows the source code as it appeared when
	the run was actually performed.
      </para>
      <informalfigure id="fig-flashlight-historical-source-view">
	<!--title>The Historical Source Snapshot View</title-->
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/flashlight-historical-source-view.png" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
    </sect3>
    <sect3>
      <title>Flashlight Monitor View</title>
      <para>
        The Monitor View provides access to the an instrumented program'sn
        runtime monitoring data.
      </para>
      <para>
        The Fields tab displays all of the fields in the program known to
        Flashlight, and their current status in the monitor.  The status of a
        field is indicated by its color.  In order to make it easier to sift
        through the data, packages and classes that contain only unobserved
        fields are displayed with a gray background.  Packages and classes
        containing any other type of fields are displayed with the default white
        background.  Currently, fields may have the following status:        
      </para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>Potential Data Race</listitem>
        <listitem>Shared and Actively Protected By A Lock</listitem>
        <listitem>Shared</listitem>
        <listitem>Not Shared</listitem>
        <listitem>Not Observed</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
      <para>
        The Locks Tab displays all current locks in the program.  Garbage
        collected locks are not displayed, as this could potentially cause the
        instrumentation to be unbounded in memory size.  Any locks that the
        runtime monitoring believes could potentially deadlock (or that are
        currently deadlocked) are displayed in red font.
      </para>
      <para>
        Finally, the EDT tab displays all of the fields in the program known to
        Flashlight, just as the Fields tab does.  Any fields that have been
        accessed both inside and outside of a Swing Event Dispatch Thread are
        highlighted.  This feature can be used to detect violations of the Swing
        threading model.
      </para>
      <informalfigure id="fig-flashlight-historical-source-view">
	<!--title>The Historical Source Snapshot View</title-->
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/flashlight-historical-source-view.png" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>

    </sect3>

  </sect2>
</sect1>



