<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../lib/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<sect1 id="quick-start">
  <title>Quick start: How to instrument your code and query
  Flashlight</title>

  <para>This section assumes that you have installed Flashlight. If you see a
  <guimenu>Flashlight</guimenu> menu item on your Eclipse main menu then you can
  assume Flashlight has been properly installed.</para>

  <para>You need to install a license to use Flashlight.  If you do not have a
  license file visit <ulink
  url="http://www.surelogic.com">http://www.surelogic.com</ulink> to obtain one.
  To install the license select <guimenuitem>Manage SureLogic
  Licenses</guimenuitem> from the <guimenu>Flashlight</guimenu> menu as shown in
  <xref linkend="fig-quick-start-license-menu" />.</para>

  <figure id="fig-quick-start-license-menu">
    <title>The menu option to install a license for Flashlight</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/quick-start-license-menu.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para> This will cause the <guilabel>Manage SureLogic Licenses</guilabel> to
  appear as shown in <xref linkend="fig-quick-start-license-dialog-empty"
  />. Highlight the Flashlight row and select the <guibutton>Install
  License</guibutton> button to install your license file.</para>

  <figure id="fig-quick-start-license-dialog-empty">
    <title>The SureLogic license management dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/quick-start-license-dialog-empty.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>Flashlight will not disrupt your Eclipse installation if a license for
  it is not installed, however, it will not allow you to use Flashlight
  functionality.  We will assume from this point on that you have installed your
  license.</para>

  <para>Flashlight is a dynamic analysis tool which means that you have to run
  your program to use it.  Flashlight instruments your program when it starts up
  and uses that instrumentation to collect data about your program.  By default,
  data resides in your workspace under a directory named
  <filename>.flashlight-data</filename>.</para>
</sect1>
