<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<sect1 id="introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para><emphasis>What is Flashlight?</emphasis> Flashlight is a dynamic
  analysis tool that helps you to understand the concurrency within your
  Java software. It is similar to a profiler in the sense that it
  collects data from a program execution and presents information about
  that run to the tool user. Flashlight casts light on issues related to
  performance, concurrency, and code safety. The Flashlight dynamic
  analysis tool is designed so that even one run can reveal information
  regarding a relatively much larger universe of runs, and thus enable
  developers to address potential issues earlier. The tool is also
  designed to afford developers and evaluators a visibility that enables
  them to develop models to support a "more complete" analysis by a
  sound static analysis tool like SureLogic's JSure.</para>

  <para>At a more technical level, Flashlight is designed to scale to
  very large amounts of collected instrumentation data. It accomplishes
  this through a unique pipeline/buffering approach that rapidly moves
  data out of the instrumented program's process heap and into secondary
  storage. It is designed to interact cleanly with garbage collection
  and object finalization.</para>

  <para>Flashlight use imposes an overhead cost, in terms of time and
  memory, on your program. Flashlight is a much more invasive analysis
  than a typical Java profiler. Roughly, an instrumented program will
  require two to three times the memory it normally uses and will run
  from 20 times to 80 times slower than it normally runs.  A dual- or
  quad-core CPU is recommend to reduce the overhead Flashlight imposes
  on the instrumented program because Flashlight is able to take
  advantage of the available hardware. Flashlight uses a large amount of
  disk space to store the data it collects, thus 50 to 100 Gigabytes of
  free disk space is recommended.</para>

  <para>Flashlight has a highly effective query capability, wherein the
  database of program run data is queried using a hierarchy of queries
  that enable the results of one query to be used as a basis for "drill
  in" using sub-queries.</para>
</sect1>
