<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="reference"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Reference</title>
  <sect1>
    <title>The JSure Menu</title>

    <figure id="fig-jsure-menu">
      <title>The JSure menu</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/jsure-menu.png"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para>The JSure menu, see <xref linkend="fig-jsure-menu"/>, appears
    as an item on the Eclipse workspace main menu. This menu provides
    direct access to common JSure commands.  The commands on the JSure
    main menu are</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Focus Verification&hellip;</title>
          <para>This command allows the user to choose which project
          should be assured by JSure.  A dialog is opened to allow the
          user to select which project to assure, as seen in <xref
          linkend="fig-focus-verification-window"/>. Assurance will be
          enabled for the selected project and disabled for all other
          projects in the workspace. </para>
        </formalpara>
        
        <figure id="fig-focus-verification-window">
          <title>The Focus Verification dialog box</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/focus-verification-window.png"/></imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Disable Verification of All Projects</title>
          <para>This command ensures that no project is selected for assurance.</para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Open Code Verification Perspective</title>
          <para>This menu choice opens the <guilabel>Code
          Verification</guilabel> perspective. This perspective is
          useful for examining the JSure assurance results;
          see <xref linkend="sec-code-verification-perspective"/>. This
          perspective may also be opened via the normal Eclipse menus
          and toolbars for perspectives.</para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Send Tip for Improvement</title>
          <para>This command opens a dialog to allow entry of a
          suggestion by the user to improve the JSure tool. For more
          information please see <xref
          linkend="sec-bugs-and-tips"/>.</para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Send Problem Report</title>
          <para>This command opens a dialog to allow entry of a problem
          report by the user about the JSure tool. For more information
          please see <xref linkend="sec-bugs-and-tips"/>.</para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <formalpara>
          <title>Manage SureLogic Licenses</title>
          <para>This command opens the SureLogic license management
          dialog. This dialog allows the user to install, view, and
          uninstall licenses for JSure and other SureLogic tools. For
          more information see <xref linkend="sec-license-management"
          />.</para>
        </formalpara>
      </listitem>          
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec-package-explorer">
    <title>Additions to the Package Explorer</title>

    <figure id="fig-license-management">
      <title>JSure additions to the <guilabel>Package Explorer</guilabel> toolbar and menu</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/toolbar-menu.png"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <figure id="fig-license-management">
      <title>JSure additions to the <guilabel>Package Explorer</guilabel> context menu</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/context-menu.png"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1 id="sec-code-verification-perspective">
    <title>The Code Verification perspective</title>
    
    <para>The <guilabel>Code Verification</guilabel> perspective organizes the Eclipse
    workbench to show views which will help you to interact with
    tool findings.</para>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Switching to the Perspective</title>
      
      <para>The <guilabel>Code Verification</guilabel> perspective can be enabled
      in several ways:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>By selecting <menuchoice><guimenu>JSure</guimenu>
            <guimenuitem>Open Code Verification
            Perspective</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.</para>
          </listitem>
          
          <listitem>
            <para>By selecting <menuchoice><guimenu>Window</guimenu>
            <guisubmenu>Open Perspective</guisubmenu>
            <guimenuitem>Other&hellip;</guimenuitem></menuchoice>, and
            then choosing <guilabel>Code Verification</guilabel> from
            the <guilabel>Open Perspective</guilabel> dialog box.</para>
          </listitem>          
          
          <listitem>
            <para>By choosing to switch to the perspective when focusing
            verification on a project:
              <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="images/perspective-switch.png" />
                </imageobject>
              </mediaobject>
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      
      <para>The only view unique to the perspective is the
      <guilabel>Verification Status</guilabel> view.  You can add this
      view to any other Eclipse perspective by choosing
      <menuchoice><guimenu>Window</guimenu> <guisubmenu>Show
      View</guisubmenu>
      <guimenuitem>Other&hellip;</guimenuitem></menuchoice> command, and
      then choosing <guilabel>Verification Status</guilabel> under the
      <guilabel>JSure</guilabel> category.</para>

      <para><emphasis>What's in the view...</emphasis></para>
          
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec-license-management">
    <title>License management</title>

    <para>JSure is commercial software and a license is required to
    use it. Licenses are obtained from SureLogic and expire after some
    period of time. Lack of a license will prohibit you from running
    assuing code.  Selecting <guimenuitem>Manage SureLogic
    Licenses</guimenuitem> from the <guimenu>JSure</guimenu> menu
    brings up the license management form as seen in <xref
    linkend="fig-license-management" />. For JSure to operate properly
    either a <emphasis>JSure</emphasis> or <emphasis>All
    Tools</emphasis> license must be installed.</para>

    <figure id="fig-license-management">
      <title>The SureLogic license management dialog</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/quick-start-license-dialog-empty.png"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>By default license installation requires internet access.
    SureLogic can, in special cases, provide licenses that do not
    require internet access. Further use of the product does not
    require internet access. If a manual uninstall is done, before
    license expiration, internet access is also required.  SureLogic
    tracks the number of times a particular license is installed and
    uninstalled. We stress that JSure does not, unlike other
    plug-ins such as MyEclipse, &ldquo;talk-back&rdquo; to SureLogic each time
    Eclipse is started.</para>

    <para>The installed license expires after a period of time
    (clearly visible to the user) and a new license has to
    be installed to continue to use JSure.</para>

    <para>Licenses can be installed more than once.  Thus, one
    license can be used for all of an organization or SureLogic can
    issue one per location or one per organizational entity.</para>

    <para>If the JSure Eclipse plug-in does not have a valid
    license it will not affect the Eclipse installation that JSure
    is installed into. The IDE will load and function normally, but
    when JSure functions are executed they will fail noting the
    lack of a license. Serviceability functions of the tool (e.g.,
    sending problem reports to SureLogic, installing and
    uninstalling licenses) function properly without a license.  The
    unlicensed JSure plug-in can be uninstalled or disabled within
    Eclipse.</para>

    <para>When you receive a license file from SureLogic it is
    installed via this dialog.  To install the license select the
    row in the license table that matches the type of license.  For
    example, if you have been sent a JSure license select the
    JSure row in the license table.  Next press the
    <guibutton>Install License</guibutton> button.  You will be
    prompted for the location of your license file.  The tool checks
    with SureLogic and reports that your license has been installed
    and returns showing information about the installed license. The
    license file is not examined by the tool after the installation
    is completed unless you install the file again (after an
    uninstall).</para>

    <para>To uninstall a license, select the row in the license
    table and press the <guibutton>Uninstall
    License</guibutton>. You will be asked if you are sure you want
    to uninstall the license.  If you confirm the uninstall then the
    license is removed.  This may take a minute as SureLogic is
    informed that your license has been uninstalled.</para>

    <para>When a license is nearing expiration the tool warns the
    user with the dialog shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-license-management-expiration-warning" /></para>

    <figure id="fig-license-management-expiration-warning">
      <title>Dialog warning that the installed JSure license is about to expire</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/license-management-expiration-warning.png"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>When a license does expire it disappears from the dialog.
    The tool is considered unlicensed at that point. To fix this
    situation install a new license (it is not required to install a
    new version of JSure).</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="sec-bugs-and-tips">
    <title>Bugs and tips</title>

    <para>JSure allows any user to send problem reports and suggestions
    to SureLogic from the main menu. Selecting
    <menuchoice><guimenu>JSure</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Send Tip for
    Improvement</guimenuitem></menuchoice> or
    <menuchoice><guimenu>JSure</guimenu> <guimenuitem>Send Problem
    Report</guimenuitem></menuchoice> allows a tip or problem report to
    be send to SureLogic directly within Eclipse as shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-bugs-and-tips-main-menu-service"/>. These menu choices
    bring up dialogs that allow the user to control exactly what
    information is sent to SureLogic.  In addition, the user can preview
    the exact text that will be sent over the internet.</para>

    <figure id="fig-bugs-and-tips-main-menu-service">
      <title>Menu items to send bugs and tips to SureLogic</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/bugs-and-tips-main-menu-service.png"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The <guimenuitem>Send Tip for Improvement</guimenuitem>
    command opens a dialog to allow entry of a suggestion by the
    user to improve the JSure tool as seen in <xref
    linkend="fig-bugs-and-tips-menu-send-tip" />. The dialog allows the
    user to control exactly what information is sent to SureLogic.
    In addition, the user can preview the exact text that will be
    sent.</para>

    <figure id="fig-bugs-and-tips-menu-send-tip">
      <title>Dialog allowing the user to enter a tip to improve JSure</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/bugs-and-tips-menu-send-tip.png"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The <guimenuitem>Send Problem Report</guimenuitem> command
    opens a dialog to allow entry of a problem report by the user
    about the JSure tool as seen in <xref
    linkend="fig-bugs-and-tips-menu-problem-report" /> The dialog
    allows the user to control exactly what information is sent to
    SureLogic.  In addition, the user can preview the exact text
    that will be sent.</para>

    <figure id="fig-bugs-and-tips-menu-problem-report">
      <title>Dialog allowing the user to enter a problem report about JSure</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/bugs-and-tips-menu-problem-report.png"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Messages sent from these dialogs go over HTTP to
    SureLogic. If a proxy is used on your network then it is
    critical to configure Eclipse to use it.  To do this open the
    Eclipse <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel> and examine the
    <guilabel>Network Connections</guilabel> under the
    <guilabel>General</guilabel> preferences.  This dialog allows
    you to configure Eclipse for your network as shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-bugs-and-tips-network-connections" /></para>

    <figure id="fig-bugs-and-tips-network-connections">
      <title>Eclipse preferences for network connections within the IDE.</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/bugs-and-tips-network-connections.png"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
