<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../lib/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<section id="sec-ant-task">
    <title>Using Ant</title>
    
    <para>The Flashlight Ant task can  can instrument a JAR or WAR to produce
        Flashlight results when the JAR or WAR is run. After the program is run,
        the output is a directory thatt can be loaded into Eclipse to examine its results.
        You load the run data into Eclipse using the <guilabel>Import Ant/Maven Scan...</guilabel>
     on the Flashlight menu. Once loaded into Eclipse the Flashlight run can be prepared and queried
     just like like any other run launched within Eclise. Note the the Ant task only works with
     Java and cannot (yet) be used to instrument an Android APK outside of Eclipse.</para>
     
     <para>The Ant tasks are not included within the Eclipse plugin (to save space) but
      can be downloaded <ulink url="http://surelogic.com/static/eclipse/install.html#cl">here</ulink> on
      the SureLogic website.</para>
     
     <para>Note that you must run this task in a Java 7 VM (it can analyze any code).</para>
     
    <section>
    <title>flashlight-instrument-archive task</title>
  
    <para>This task instruments a JAR or WAR and produces 
        another JAR or WAR. The attributes are:</para>
       
    <informaltable frame='all'>
      <tgroup cols='3' align='left'>
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Attribute</entry>
            <entry>Description</entry>
            <entry>Required</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <row>
            <entry>srcfile</entry>
            <entry>
              This attribute sets the path to the JAR or WAR to instrument. This file is not changed by the task. <code>srcfile="server.jar"</code>
            </entry>
            <entry>Yes</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>destfile</entry>
            <entry>
              This attribute sets set the output JAR or WAR to create (or overwrite).
               <code>destfile="flserver.jar"</code>
            </entry>
            <entry>Yes</entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>runtime</entry>
            <entry>
              This attribute sets location of the flashlight runtime. Normally this is set by a property in your script.
             <code>runtime="${flashlight.runtime}"</code>
            </entry>
            <entry>Yes</entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    
    </section>
  
  <para>For a concrete example, please see the tutorial in <xref linkend="sec-tutorial-ant" />.</para>
  
</section>
