<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../lib/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<section id="flashlight-menu">
  <title>The Flashlight menu</title>

  <figure id="fig-menu-flashlight">
    <title>The Flashlight menu</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/menu-flashlight.png"/></imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>The <guimenu>Flashlight</guimenu> menu appears as an item on the Eclipse
  workspace main menu. This menu provides direct access to common commands. The
  menu is divided into four sections. The top section contains command to launch and load
  instrumented programs (in Eclipse or via Ant) and a command to show the launched run
  control dialog and
  the <guilabel>Flashlight</guilabel> perspective. The second section allows access to
  the JSure inference capabilities of Flashlight. The third section contains
  commands to report problems about or suggest improvements to Flashlight
  directly to SureLogic. The bottom section allows access to the license
  management dialog.</para>

  <para>The commands on the Flashlight menu are:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
        <title><guimenuitem>Flashlight</guimenuitem></title>
        <para>Lets a user rerun a recent Flashlight run configuration or create
        a new one using the <guilabel>Flashlight Configurations</guilabel>
        view.</para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
        <title><guimenuitem>Import Ant run...</guimenuitem></title>
        <para>Allows the user to copy a Flashlight run created from one of the
        Flashlight Ant tasks into the data directory. This allows the run to be
        prepared and inspected in the Eclipse tool user experience.  For more information
        about using Ant with Flashlight please see <xref
        linkend="flashlight-ant-tasks" />.</para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
	<title><guimenuitem>Save Ant Task As...</guimenuitem></title>
	<para>Saves the Flashlight Ant tasks to a directory of your choice.
	These tasks are primarily used to collect Flashlight data when a program
	cannot be launched directly from Eclipse.  For more information please
	see <xref linkend="flashlight-ant-tasks" />.</para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
        <title><guimenuitem>Launched Run Control...</guimenuitem></title>
        <para>Opens the <guilabel>Flashlight Launched Run Control</guilabel> dialog. This
        dialog lists all instrumented programs launched during this Eclipse session. It allows
        collection of data to be stopped at any time.</para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
        <title><guimenuitem>Open Flashlight Perspective</guimenuitem></title>
        <para>Opens the <guilabel>Flashlight</guilabel> perspective. This
        perspective is useful for examining and querying collected run
        data. This perspective may also be opened via the normal Eclipse menus
        and toolbars for perspectives.</para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
        <title><guimenuitem>Flashlight Android APK...</guimenuitem></title>
        <para>Opens a dialog that allows the user to select an APK file, which is a packaged Android application (binary),
            and launch an instrumented run on an Android device or emulator. Optionally you can associated a
            workspace project with the APK, but this is only useful if you have the application's source
            code, and is rarely needed because the Android project can be launched directly with Flashlight.
              For more information please see <xref linkend="flashlight-apk" />.</para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
        <title><guimenuitem>Infer JSure Annotations...</guimenuitem></title>
        <para>Opens a dialog that allows the user to infer JSure annotations for
        a project, based on a completed Flashlight run.  For more information
        see <xref linkend="flashlight-promises-inference" />.</para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
        <title><guimenuitem>Send Tip for Improvement</guimenuitem></title>
        <para>Opens a dialog to allow entry of a suggestion by the user to
        improve Flashlight. For more information please see <xref
        linkend="sec-bugs-and-tips"/>.</para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
        <title><guimenuitem>Send Problem Report</guimenuitem></title>
        <para>Opens a dialog to allow entry of a problem report by the user
        about Flashlight. For more information please see <xref
        linkend="sec-bugs-and-tips"/>.</para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
	<title><guimenuitem>Run Flashlight Tutorials</guimenuitem></title>
	<para>Opens a dialog to allow the user to import tutorial projects into
	their workspace and open the Flashlight help to the step by step
	tutorials.  For more information please see <xref
	linkend="sec-tutorial"/>.</para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <formalpara>
        <title><guimenuitem>Manage SureLogic Licenses</guimenuitem></title>
        <para>Opens the SureLogic license management dialog. This dialog allows
        the user to install, view, and uninstall licenses for Flashlight and
        other SureLogic tools. For more information see <xref
        linkend="sec-license-management" />.</para>
      </formalpara>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

</section>
