<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../lib/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="release-notes">
  <title>Release notes</title>
  
  <para>For each release of Flashlight there are new and noteworthy
  features to try out, and known limitations to avoid or workaround.
  These are presented in the sections below for each released version of
  Flashlight.</para>
    <section>
    <title>Flashlight version 5.5.0</title>
    <para>This section describes the 5.5.0 version of Flashlight.</para>
    <section>
      <title>New and Noteworthy</title>
      <para>This section describes new and noteworthy features in this version of Flashlight.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Java 8 language and virtual machine support</emphasis> &mdash; This release of Flashlight
          fully supports the Java 8 programming language and virtual machine. The tool also supports running older
          Java programs on a Java 8 virtual machine. To launch Java 8 programs a version of Eclipse that
          supports Java 8, e.g., Eclipse Luna (4.4) or above, is required.</para>
        </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>New query to detect multiple acquisitions and releases of the same lock within a method</emphasis> &mdash;
          This release of Flashlight has a new query <emphasis>What methods acquire locks in more than one place?</emphasis> which
          is useful for uncovering potential locking problems. In particular, if a lock is released and then
          reacquired during a method it could indicate that a class-level invariant is not established
          and some other code could see the object in an "in-between" state.</para>
          <para>Because Flashlight does not understand the invariants that must be maintained in your code, this
          query may not be precise for all systems. But it can be useful in uncovering subtle locking problems.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Flashlight version 5.4.0</title>
    <para>This section describes the 5.4.0 version of Flashlight.</para>
    <section>
      <title>New and Noteworthy</title>
      <para>This section describes new and noteworthy features in this version of Flashlight.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Binary Android APK Launch Support</emphasis> &mdash;
              A new Flashlight menu item has been added to launch
              binary Android applications on an Android device. Binary Android applications
              are contained within an APK file.
              
            <mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/release-notes-540-apk.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
          </para>
          <para>This release is the first that makes this capability accessible from the tool menu.
          Note that you must have the ADT loaded in your Eclipse and load the "Flashlight Client Android (Optional)" feature
          when you install the SureLogic tools.</para>
          <para>The only limitation we are aware of with this new feature is that you cannot use
          it to "overwrite" default-, root-, or vendor-installed applications on your phone.
          The apps included in this set vary from carrier to carrier &mdash; but typically includes GMail,
          Camera and some other applications. We are currently investigating approaches to
          avoid this limitation.</para>
          <para>For more information please see <xref linkend="flashlight-apk" />.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis>Duration totals corrected</emphasis> &mdash; A bug
        that caused the total duration reported in several Flashlight queries to be incorrect has been fixed
        in this release. An example is hilighted in the image below.
          <mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/release-notes-540-durationtotal.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
        </para></listitem>
       </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  
    <section>
    <title>Flashlight version 5.1.0</title>
    <para>This section describes the 5.1.0 version of Flashlight.</para>
    <section>
      <title>New and Noteworthy</title>
      <para>This section describes new and noteworthy features in this version of Flashlight.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Dynamic analysis instrumentation made more concurrent to reduce overhead</emphasis> &mdash;
              This release contains several changes to the dynamic analysis data store used by Flashlight
              to collect data from both standard Java programs and Android applications. These
              changes reduce the overhead of the tool's instrumentation for most applications.
          </para>
        </listitem>
       </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Flashlight version 5.0.0</title>
    <para>This section describes the 5.0.0 version of Flashlight.</para>
    <section>
      <title>New and Noteworthy</title>
      <para>This section describes new and noteworthy features in this version of Flashlight.</para>
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Query Results shows good and bad news about the selected run</emphasis> &mdash;
              The <guilabel>Query Results</guilabel> view now shows either (a) an overview of the run
      currently selected in the <guilabel>Flashlight Runs</guilabel> view or (b) query results as
      a table, tree or tree-table. What is new is the lists of good and bad
      news items about the selected run. These news items are not definitive, because they represent
      information from a single run of the program&mdash;hence the name <emphasis>news</emphasis> instead of <emphasis>results</emphasis>.
      Some news items are underlined. These underlined news items may be selected with the mouse to invoke a query and show the
      news item's corresponding results. Some news items are not underlined because they indicate that no information was
      observed during the run&mdash;in these cases no results indicates something newsworthy. These items that are not
      underlined have no associated
      results.
          </para>
          <para>The screenshot below shows an example of good and bad news about
              a run of the <guilabel>FlashlightTutorial_CounterRace</guilabel> Android application.
              
              <mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/release-notes-500-news.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Major changes to tool queries</emphasis> &mdash;
              The set of queries and sub-queries available in Flashlight has been significantly changed. These changes
              make the tool easier to use and more actionable. In particular, these changes make it easier to get to
              stack traces and lock traces and, therefore, link an analysis result to your code.
              </para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para><emphasis>Stack and lock traces are now unique</emphasis> &mdash;
              Flashlight now identifies each stack and lock trace uniquely. This changes the way many queries are reported.
              The problem which could occur in past versions of Flashight is that a query could result in hundreds of rows.
              Now queries can group by distinct stack trace or lock trace and dramatically reduce the on-screen clutter.
              The updated queries present more information to the user in a concise manner.
              </para>
              <para>As an example, the screenshot below shows the query results about where the field <guilabel>f_threadLocalCounts</guilabel> is
                  accessed in the code.</para>
                  
              <mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/release-notes-500-uTrace.png" />
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
			
                  <para>The result is grouped by unique path to the access&mdash;or unique stack trace. This result is three
                  rows, in the previous release of Flashlight this result would have been 1,874 rows. In addition, this result conveys at a
                  glance more about the use of the <guilabel>f_threadLocalCounts</guilabel> field by the program.
                  In particular, the field is initialized in the main thread, passed to Thread-272 where
                  it is thread confined for almost a second, then, finally, read again by the main thread. This insight would
                  be hard to obtain from a list of 1,874 accesses.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
  </section>

</chapter>
