<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../../lib/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<sect1 id="tutorials"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <title>Tutorials</title>

  <para>This section contains tutorials demonstrating the use of
  JSure and its program annotations to assure the correct use of
  locks in concurrent Java programs.  The first two tutorials use small
  closed-world examples to demonstrate annotating code and using JSure, starting
  with no annotations at all.  The
  remaining turorials begin with a partially annotated program,
  and demonstrate more sophisticated concepts such as support for
  <package>java.util.concurrent</package> reader&ndash;writer
  locks.</para>

  <figure id="fig-tutorial-installing-projects">
    <title>Menu item to install tutorial projects into your workspace</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/tutorial-installing-projects.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  <para>These tutorials assume that you have installed JSure. If you
  see a <guimenu>JSure</guimenu> menu item on your Eclipse main menu
  than you can assume it has been installed properly.  To follow along
  with the tutorials you will also need to add the tutorial projects to
  your workspace.  From the Eclipse main menu, choose
  <menuchoice><guimenu>JSure</guimenu><guimenuitem>Run JSure
  Tutorials</guimenuitem></menuchoice> and add the projects to your
  workspace as displayed in <xref
  linkend="fig-tutorial-installing-projects" /> and <xref
  linkend="fig-tutorial-jsure-install" />.</para>
  
  	<note>
		<title>Do not use the Uniqueness Verifying Analysis</title>

		<para>Please ensure that <guilabel>Use Uniqueness Verifying Analysis</guilabel> is
		<emphasis>not checked</emphasis> as shown in <xref linkend="fig-tutorial-installing-projects" />.
		This analysis is not recommended for use in the current release and is not used in the following
		tutorials. The tool default is that it is not checked, but please double-check this setting
		before you start working through a tutorial.</para>
	</note>
  
  <figure id="fig-tutorial-jsure-install">
    <title>Adding tutorial projects to your workspace</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
	<imagedata fileref="images/tutorial-jsure-install.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

	<note>
		<title>Several of the imported projects will not compile in Eclipse</title>

		<para>The JSureTutorial_PlanetBaron and JSureTutorial_EffectiveEffects
		projects will <emphasis>not</emphasis> compile without errors until you add the Promises
		Library JAR into the build path of each project. A few of the tutorial
		projects, such as <classname>JSureTutorial_ThreadSafeAndImmutable</classname>,
		compile without errors because no annotations have been placed into the projects yet.</para>
	</note>
    
    <para>Next, we need to add the
    SureLogic annotation types in the package <package>com.surelogic</package>
    to each tutorial project's class path.  This is most easily done
    by allowing JSure to do it for us:
    
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>Select
	<menuchoice><guimenuitem>JSure</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Add/Update
	Promises Library in Project...</guimenuitem></menuchoice> from
	the Eclipse menu.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>Press <application>Select All</application> in the
	dialog which appears. If you did not start with an empty Eclipse
	workspace, you may want to uncheck any of your own projects that appear in this dialog.

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="images/tutorial-add-promises-jar.png" />
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>

	Then press <guilabel>OK</guilabel> to add the promises JAR to
	each project's classpath.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    All the tutorial projects should now compile in your Eclipse workspace without errors.</para>

  <xi:include href="sect2-jcip.xml"/>
  
  <xi:include href="sect2-boundedfifo.xml"/>
  
  <xi:include href="sect2-planetbaron.xml"/>
  
  <xi:include href="sect2-util.concurrent.xml"/>

  <xi:include href="sect2-effects/sect2.xml"/>
  
  <!-- xi:include href="sect2-smallworld.xml"/ -->
</sect1>
