<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../lib/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="release-notes">
  <title>Release notes</title>
  
  <para>For each release of Flashlight there are new and noteworthy
  features to try out, and known limitations to avoid or workaround.
  These are presented in the sections below for each released version of
  Flashlight.</para>
	
	
  <sect1>
    <title>Flashlight version 2.3.0</title>
    
    <para>This section describes the 2.3.0 release of Flashlight.</para>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>New and Noteworthy</title>

      <para>This section describes new and noteworthy features in this
      version of Flashlight.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>The Flashlight Status view provides a quick overview of a
	    run's results.</emphasis> &mdash; A new view has been added to make
	    it easier to tell if there are interesting results from a prepared
	    run.  The Flashlight Status view indicates if the lock cycle
	    analysis has found any potential deadlocks or if the lock set
	    analysis has detected any possible race conditions.  You can
	    double-click on a warning indicator to run the relevant query.
	    <mediaobject>
	      <imageobject>
		<imagedata fileref="images/flashlight-status-view.png" />
	      </imageobject>
	    </mediaobject>
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Known Problems</title>

      <para>This section describes known bugs and limitations in this
      version of Flashlight.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    <emphasis>Preparing very large files will sometimes fail.</emphasis>
	    &mdash; Due to a limitation in Flashlight's embedded database
	    implementation, Flashlight is unable to prepare very large files.
	    The maximum size file that can be prepared depends on
	    characteristics of the instrumented program, but as a general rule
	    you shouldn't encounter this problem until your raw file is &gt; 300
	    MB in size.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
