<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<book lang="en-US">

<title>Flashlight User Guide</title>
<subtitle>How to use and configure the Flashlight Eclipse client</subtitle>
<bookinfo>
  <copyright>
    <year>2008</year>
    <holder>SureLogic Inc.</holder>
  </copyright>
  <legalnotice>
    <para>The authors and publishers have taken care in the
    preparation of this documentation, but make no expressed or
    implied warranty of any kind and assume no responsibility for
    errors and omissions. No liability is assumed for incidental or
    consequential damages in connection with or arising out of the use
    of the information or programs herein.</para>
  </legalnotice>
  <pubdate>Version 1.0&mdash;November 2008</pubdate>
</bookinfo>

<chapter id="preface">
  <title>Preface</title>
  <section>
    <title>Audience</title>
    <para>This document is intended for Java developers who want to
    use the Flashlight tool within the Eclipse Java IDE. We assume
    that the reader understands both the Java programming language and
    the use of Eclipse for Java development.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Contact information</title>
    <para>For technical support or other questions, please
    contact:</para>
    <para><email>support@surelogic.com</email></para>
    <para>5808 Forbes Avenue, Pittsburgh, PA 15217-1602</para>
  </section>
</chapter>

<chapter id="getting-started">
  <title>Getting started</title>
  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><emphasis>What is Flashlight?</emphasis> Flashlight is a
    dynamic analysis tool that helps you to better understand the
    concurrency within your Java software. It is similar to a profiler
    in the sense that it collects data from a program execution and
    presents information about that run to the tool user. Flashlight
    casts light on issues related to performance, concurrency, and
    code safety. The Flashlight dynamic analysis tool is designed so
    that even one run can reveal information regarding a relatively
    much larger universe of runs, and thus enable developers to
    address potential issues earlier. The tool is also designed to
    afford developers and evaluators a visibility that enables them to
    develop models to support "more complete" analyses such as sound
    static analysis, such as SureLogic's JSure tool.</para>

    <para>At a more technical level, Flashlight is designed to scale
    to very large amounts of collected instrumentation data. It
    accomplishes this through a unique pipeline/buffering approach
    that rapidly moves data out of the instrumented program's process
    heap and into secondary storage. It is designed to interact
    cleanly with garbage collection and object finalization.</para>

    <para>Flashlight use imposes an overhead cost, in terms of time
    and memory, on your program.  Flashlight is a much more invasive
    analysis than a typical Java profiler.  Roughly, an instrumented
    program will require two to three times the memory it normally
    uses and will run from 20 times to 80 times slower than it
    normally runs.  A dual- or quad-core CPU is recommend to speed the
    instrumented program.  Flashlight uses a large amount of disk
    space to store the data it collects, thus 50 to 100 Gigabytes of
    free disk space are recommended.</para>

    <para>The tool also has a highly effective query capability,
    wherein the database is queried using a hierarchy of queries that
    enable the results of one query to be used as a basis for "drill
    in" using sub-queries.</para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Quick start: How to instrument your code and query
    Flashlight</title>

    <para>This section assumes that you have installed Flashlight. If
    you see a <guimenu>Flashlight</guimenu> menu item on your Eclipse
    main menu then you can assume Flashlight has been properly
    installed.</para>

    <para>You need to install a license to use Flashlight.  If you do
    not have a license file visit <ulink
    url="http://www.surelogic.com">http://www.surelogic.com</ulink> to
    obtain one.  To install the license select <guimenuitem>Manage
    SureLogic Licenses</guimenuitem> from the
    <guimenu>Flashlight</guimenu> menu as shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-quick-start-license-menu" /></para>

    <figure id="fig-quick-start-license-menu">
      <title>The menu option to install a license for Flashlight.</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject role="html">
	  <imagedata fileref="images/quick-start-license-menu.png" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para> This will cause the <guilabel>Manage SureLogic
    Licenses</guilabel> to appear as shown in <xref
    linkend="fig-quick-start-license-dialog-empty" /> Highlight the
    Flashlight row and select the <guibutton>Install
    License</guibutton> button to install your license file.</para>

    <figure id="fig-quick-start-license-dialog-empty">
      <title>The SureLogic license management dialog.</title>
      <mediaobject>
	<imageobject role="html">
	  <imagedata fileref="images/quick-start-license-dialog-empty.png" />
	</imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Flashlight will not disrupt your Eclipse installation if a
    license for it is not installed, however, it will not allow you to
    use Flashlight functionality.  We will assume from this point on
    that you have installed your license.</para>

    <para>Flashlight is a dynamic analyis tool which means that you
    have to run your program to use it.  Flashlight instruments your
    program when it starts up and uses that instrumentation to collect
    data about your program.  Data is collected to a file located in
    <filename>~/.flashlight-data</filename>.</para>

  </section>
</chapter>

<chapter id="reference">
  <title>Reference</title>
  <section>
    <title>The Flashlight menu</title>
    <para>The Flashlight menu appears as an item on the Eclipse
    workspace main menu.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>The Flashlight perspective</title>
    <para>The Flashlight perspective organizes the Eclipse workbench
    to show views which will help you to interact with tool
    findings.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>Release notes</title>
  <para>For each release of Flashlight there are new and noteworthy
    features to try out, and known limitations to avoid or
    workaround. These are presented in the sections below for each
    released version of Flashlight.</para>
  <section>
    <title>Flashlight version 1.0</title>
    <para>This section describes the 1.0 release of Flashlight.</para>
    <section>
      <title>New and Noteworthy</title>
      <para>This section describes new and noteworthy features in this
      version of Flashlight.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Known Problems</title>
      <para>This section describes known bugs and limitations in this
      version of Flashlight.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>

</book>