<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"../../../../lib/docbook-xml-4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<sect1 id="extended-model2">
  <title>Extending the Model: Aggregating Arrays and Other
  Objects</title>
      
  <para>An array in Java is a separate object from the object whose
  field refers to the array. Protecting an array-typed field thus
  protects <emphasis>the reference to the array only</emphasis>. It is
  not sufficient to extend the protection to the elements of the array:
  we also need to know that the array object is accessible through that
  field only. If the array could be referenced through other fields,
  then it would still be possible to access it concurrently because the
  locking model could be bypassed by accessing the array through a
  different field.</para>

  <para>Much of the time, however, it is not intended that an array is
  aliased; in these cases, the array can be incorporated into the state
  of the object that references it.  We call this <emphasis>aggregating
  state</emphasis>. In the simplest case, an array is aggregated into
  the object that references it by adding a single annotation to the
  field that references the array:
      
    <programlisting>
<emphasis>@Unique</emphasis>
private Object[] myArray;
    </programlisting>
      
  This does two things:

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>Declares the programmer’s intent that the field is
      the only field that references the array object it references.  A
      separate analysis is used to assure that a
      <classname>@Unique</classname> field is never aliased.  A new
      expression always creates an unaliased object, so it is always
      safe to assign the results of a new expression to a
      <classname>@Unique</classname> field.</para></listitem>
  
      <listitem><para>Extends the state of the referencing object to
      include the elements of the array. State aggregation is not
      automatically transitive; thus if the array elements are object references,
      those objects are not aggregated, only the references to
      them.</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </para>
      
  <para>In the example below, the constructor
  <function>Buffer(Object[])</function> does not assure because it
  assigns an array to field buf that might be aliased, conflicting with
  the <classname>@Unique</classname> annotation on the field. The
  assignment to buf in the constructor <function>Buffer(int)</function>
  assures because it assigns a fresh array to the field.  The lock
  <structfield>Lock</structfield> does not need to be held to access the
  field <structfield>buf</structfield> because it is <code>final</code>.
  The implementation of <function>copyContents()</function> does not
  assure because even though <structfield>Lock</structfield> does not
  need to be held to access the field <structfield>buf</structfield> or
  the field <structfield>length</structfield>,
  <structfield>Lock</structfield> must be held to access the contents of
  the array referenced by <structfield>buf</structfield>.  Analysis
  knows that the method <function>System.arraycopy()</function> reads
  from the <structfield>Instance</structfield> region of its first
  parameter, and thus via aggregation, reads from the
  <structfield>Instance</structfield> region of the
  <classname>Buffer</classname> object.  (This analysis is informed by
  effects analysis and annotations, described in <xref
  linkend="method-effects"/>.)</para>
      
  <programlisting>
<emphasis>@RegionLock("Lock is this protects Instance")</emphasis>
public class Buffer {
  <emphasis>@Unique</emphasis>
  private final Object[] buf;
  &hellip;
  public Buffer(int size) {
    this.buf = new Object[size]; // good!
  }
  &hellip;
  public Buffer(Object[] newBuffer) {
    this.buf = newBuffer; // bad!
  }

  public Object[] copyContents() {
    final Object[] copy = new Object[this.buf.length];
    System.arraycopy(this.buf, 0, copy, 0, this.buf.length);
    return copy;
  }
}
  </programlisting>
      
  <para>Aggregation applies not only to arrays, but to objects in
  general.  So any object-typed field can be declared
  <classname>@Unique</classname> and have its state aggregated into the
  state of its referring object. In practice, aggregation of collections
  is common. The code below aggregates the set <code>log</code> into the
  <code>Instance</code> region.</para>

  <programlisting>
public class LogExample {
  @Unique
  private final Set&lt;String&gt; log = new HashSet&lt;String&gt;();
  &hellip;
}
  </programlisting>
  
  <para>The annotation <classname>@UniqueInRegion</classname> is used
  when the state of the referenced object should be aggregated into a
  named region other than <code>Instance</code>. (Declaring a named
  region is further described in a later section.) The code below
  declares a named region <code>LogData</code> and aggregates the set
  <code>log</code> into it.</para>

  <programlisting>
@Region("private LogData")
public class LogExample {
  @UniqueInRegion("LogData")
  private final Set&lt;String&gt; log = new HashSet&lt;String&gt;();
  &hellip;
}
  </programlisting>
</sect1>
